<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Scott Stephens</title>
 <link href="www.scott.stephens.name/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="www.scott.stephens.name/"/>
 <updated>2016-08-13T12:38:30-05:00</updated>
 <id>www.scott.stephens.name</id>
 <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <email>stephens.js@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>About the Work Timer</title>
   <link href="www.scott.stephens.name/2016/08/12/about-the-work-timer/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>www.scott.stephens.name/2016/08/12/about-the-work-timer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made the work timer primarily as an exercise to learn some javascript and CSS, but I thought it might be worth describing how I use it, in case anyone stumbles upon it and is curious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often work with a variation of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro Timer&lt;/a&gt; productivity system. For the first 25 minutes after starting work, I keep working regardless of how frustrated I feel. After the first 25 minutes, I take a 5-10 minute break whenever I feel even a little frustrated. It helps me perserve long enough when starting work to get into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)&quot;&gt;flow&lt;/a&gt;, but break often enough that I don’t get excessively fatigued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existing pomodoro timers I found online didn’t work great with my modifications. At the end of a work period they would tend to either alert until the user interacted with the timer, or they would alert and then automatically go into the following break period. Either made it necessary for me to interact with the software at the end of the initial work period, which would sometimes knock me out of flow. So at the end of a work or break period, my timer makes a minimally obtrusive alert, then keeps counting the time. When I’ve decided I want to stop, I can tell the timer I’ve switched to a different period. It also tracks my history, so I can see how much actual working I’m doing every day, essentially gamifying my productivity efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a pure productivity standpoint writing a customized timer would have been a huge loser (given how much time I spent learning javascript and CSS). But it was a great project for learning. And I got a tool I can actually use as a bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hello World!</title>
   <link href="www.scott.stephens.name/2016/08/11/hello-world/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>www.scott.stephens.name/2016/08/11/hello-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I created this site primarily as a learning exercise. I program a lot, but, unlike a lot of other programmers, what I program typically has nothing whatsoever to do with the world wide web. Or even a corporate intra-web. Given the ubiquity of web apps I thought it might be a good idea to be at least minimally familiar with web programming. Enough that when developers talk about web stuff my blank uncomprehending stare doesn’t make them wonder if I really know how to program at all. Backend web stuff is actually pretty similar to the stuff I do every day, so for me this was mostly about the front-end, client-side web. Since for me learning by doing is the only way to go, I needed to make a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with using Jekyll to generate a static site, since that seemed like the easiest possible way to get a useful site. After realizing just how easy that was, I realized I needed a more substantial project if I actually wanted to learn anything. I’ve been using Pomodoro timers as a productivity tool recently, and decided that writing my own would make a good project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After building the site it seemed silly not to actually publish it, so here it is. I guess I have a blog now. I don’t know that I will end up posting with any regularity, but who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
