<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Scott Stephens</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2023-03-24T10:27:30-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Scott Stephens</name>
   <email>stephens.js@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Dell XPS 13 9350 Replacement Battery: My Experience</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/25/xps-9350-replacement-battery/"/>
   <updated>2019-02-25T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/25/xps-9350-replacement-battery</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-short-story&quot;&gt;The short story:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to replace a battery in a Dell XPS 9350, consider a refurbished replacement directly from Dell. They’re not available through the website, but if you contact tech support they’ll sell you one for $81 plus tax and your old battery. Or $113.17 plus tax if you want to keep the old battery. My refurb came with 53.793 WHr full charge capacity, which is 93.5% of the design capacity (57.532 WHr) and 96% of the marketing specs (56 WHr) for XPS 9350 batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-long-story&quot;&gt;The long story:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a month ago I decided it was time to replace my laptop battery. My ~2.5 year old Dell XPS 9350 was still meeting my computing needs while plugged in, but the battery was only lasting 90 minutes or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/media/xps-9350-replacement-battery/battery-report-before.png&quot; alt=&quot;Window&apos;s battery report shows my old battery had 8.542 watt-hours of full charge capacity, 14.8% of the design capacity of 57.532 watt-hours.&quot; title=&quot;Old Battery&apos;s Windows Battery Report&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consensus on the web seems to be that a third party replacement battery is the way to go. However, after some research I decided to go with a replacement part directly from Dell. This post is to document my reasoning and experience in case it’s useful to others in a similar situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I see it, there are basically four options for replacing a laptop battery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a low quality third party battery&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a high quality third party battery&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an original battery sold by a reseller&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;an original battery direct from the manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low quality third party batteries seem to run about $50. They’re easy to find on Amazon, but I won’t distinguish them with a link. They tend to get a fair amount of pretty nasty reviews. Judging from the reviews, I would say a fair number of them are dead on arrival, and that they tend not to hold up very well, with substantial degradation of capacity within 6 months. I was not very interested in replacing my battery every 6 months, so I eliminated those as an option fairly quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really only found one third party battery seller that seemed to emphasize quality: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.laptopbatteryexpress.com&quot;&gt;laptopbatteryexpress.com&lt;/a&gt;. I didn’t end up buying one from there, so I can’t speak from experience about whether it’s BS or not, but purely from reading their marketing copy they seemed a lot more trustworthy than most sellers. That comes at a price though, they wanted $110 bucks for a battery. What eventually soured me on them was that they were selling a 51 WHr battery, and the original in my laptop was a 56 WHr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original batteries from third party sellers are also easy to find on Amazon. Assuming they are legitimate products, and not illegally labeled knock-offs, I wondered where they got their supply, and if they were likely to be old batteries. Batteries degrade even if they’re not being used, so I wasn’t excited about buying a two year old battery, even if the number of charge cycles was low. They’re also expensive, costing $110.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our last option is an original battery directly from the manufacturer, in this case Dell. For a while, I thought this wasn’t an option at all: the Dell website didn’t list any XPS 9350 batteries for sale. However, I was able to buy one by asking their tech support via online chat. Slight catch though: it’s a refurbished battery, not a brand new one. Here’s what the Dell support agent had to say about what refurbished means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Me: what does refurbished mean exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dell: Well, it is not exactly new part. The systems that are returned back to us by the customers who cancel the order or the systems that are shipped back to us due to any sort of cosmetic damage on them, we take the parts out and use them for singular purpose&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dell: So it doesn’t mean that the life will be less or it will degrade soon&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dell: But the parts go through rigorous tests before they are made available for sale&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Me: so i can expect the battery to perform about as well as the original new battery in my laptop did?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dell: Absolutely&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installation was a very straightforward process, but I had trouble getting the screws out without stripping them. Doing a little reading after the fact, I think the problem might have been that they were JIS screws, and I was using a Phillips head driver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first boot on the new battery, the Windows battery report (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;powercfg /batteryreport&lt;/code&gt;) showed a full charge capacity of 53.793 WHr. That’s 93.5% of the design capacity (57.532 WHr) and 96% of the marketing specs (56 WHr) for XPS 9350 batteries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/media/xps-9350-replacement-battery/battery-report-after.png&quot; alt=&quot;Window&apos;s battery report shows my new battery has 53.793 watt-hours of full charge capacity, 93.5% of the design capacity of 57.532 watt-hours.&quot; title=&quot;New Battery&apos;s Windows Battery Report&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of the refurbished battery was $81 plus tax and the return of my old battery. Or $113.17 plus tax if I wanted to keep my old battery. I was satisfied with what I got for the price, given my alternatives. However I also think Dell’s claim that the battery life and speed of degradation are the same as with a new battery is inaccurate. It took approximately 10 months of usage on my original battery before it had degraded to the point at which the refurb came out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The return process was a bit of a hassle. First of all, they didn’t tell me ahead of time that they wanted my old battery back. It was mentioned for the first time in an email shortly after I got the final order confirmation (which didn’t mention it either). I was annoyed on principle, but mostly didn’t care, because what was I going to do with an old dead battery anyway? After I swapped batteries, it became more of an issue (more on that later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first annoyance with the return process was that there were no return shipping instructions in the package containing the new battery. For reasons I cannot fathom, Dell’s customer service phone reps were also unable to help me figure out where to send the old battery. Return shipping instructions eventually arrived by email 13 days after I received the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second annoyance with the return process came from the fact that my old battery was somewhat swollen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/media/xps-9350-replacement-battery/batteries-side-by-side.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A picture of my old and new batteries side by side shows that the old battery was swollen.&quot; title=&quot;Batteries Side By Side&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard that swollen batteries pose a larger fire risk than undamaged batteries, so I was worried that my old battery was unsafe to ship back to Dell. Indeed, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fedex.com/content/dam/fedex/us-united-states/services/Shipping-Lithium-Batteries-via-FedEx-Ground.pdf&quot;&gt;guidance published by FedEx Ground&lt;/a&gt; says that shipping damaged batteries requires coordination with the FedEx Ground safety department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I called Dell to ask if they could either offer their assurances that shipping the battery was safe or relieve me from the obligations to return it. If you’re in a similar boat I would not recommend calling Dell. I spent about an hour on the phone with absolutely nothing to show for it. Emailing the address on the return instructions eventually yielded permission not to return it without getting charged for the privilege.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I was reasonably satisfied with my purchase. I got a decent quality battery at a decent price. I think it’s a path worth considering if you’re in a similar position.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dell XPS 13 9350 SSD Upgrade: SATA to NVMe</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/10/23/xps-9350-ssd-upgrade/"/>
   <updated>2016-10-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/23/xps-9350-ssd-upgrade</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently upgraded my Dell XPS 13 9350’s SSD from the stock 128 GB Samsung CM-871 to a 512 GB Intel 600p.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It’s a somewhat unusual upgrade because the CM-871 is a SATA 3 drive, and the 600p is an NVMe drive. In most machines swapping a SATA drive for an NVMe drive will not work. But it will with the XPS 9350. While the 128 GB version comes with a SATA drive, the models with 256 and 512 GB of storage both come with NVMe drives. So the motherboard supports both SATA and NVMe. Several owners have reported their success upgrading their 128 GB drive to a Samsung 950 Pro&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. However,  in all the reports I’ve found those upgraders did a fresh install of Windows 10, rather than cloning their drive and keeping their installed programs, settings, and data. I’ve managed this latter feat, and I thought it might be worth documenting my experience in case it helps others. Read on, and you’ll learn how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you get started, make sure you have the following on hand:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 usb drives of at least 8 GB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A USB hard drive with at least 128 GB free&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A torx T5 screwdriver&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A philips head 1.2 mm screwdriver. A phillips #000 is probably roughly the same size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upgrade procedure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a Ubuntu Live USB (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubuntu.com/download/desktop&quot;&gt;download&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ubuntu.com/download/desktop/create-a-usb-stick-on-windows&quot;&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt;)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;When working with Rufus, select the ISO image first, even though it’s at the bottom of the form. It resets the other settings.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Choose a GPT partition table for UEFI only.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use FAT32 as the file system.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.macrium.com/reflectfree.aspx&quot;&gt;Macrium Reflect&lt;/a&gt; and use it to create a backup image of your existing SSD AND to create rescue media.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Good tutorial of using Reflect to backup and restore, as well as the physical drive replacement: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laptopmag.com/articles/upgrade-dell-xps-13-ssd&quot;&gt;http://www.laptopmag.com/articles/upgrade-dell-xps-13-ssd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test the Reflect rescue disk, and the Ubuntu live disk.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Press F12 to trigger the boot menu on the XPS 9350.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You may need to add options to the boot menu. It’s in the General-&amp;gt;Boot Sequence menu inside the UEFI/BIOS settings.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the physical drive replacement.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laptopmag.com/articles/upgrade-dell-xps-13-ssd&quot;&gt;laptop magazine article&lt;/a&gt; referenced earlier.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Note that they erroneosly call for a pentalobe screwdriver; you actually need a torx.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Boot into the Reflect rescue environment, restore your image to the new disk.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Again, see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laptopmag.com/articles/upgrade-dell-xps-13-ssd&quot;&gt;laptop magazine article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Boot using your newly installed disk to confirm the restore worked.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restart the computer and boot into the Ubuntu Live environment. Use gparted to adjust the size of your partitions.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In order for Ubuntu to be able to find the NVME hard drive, you need to change a UEFI/BIOS setting. You’ll be changing the storage controller from RAID mode to AHCI mode. It’s in the System Configuration-&amp;gt;SATA Operation menu.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Assuming you haven’t changed the factory partitions, you’ll have 4 on the old hard drive: a 500 MB boot partition, a 128 MB reserved partition, a ~127.8 GB data and OS partition, and a 850 MB recovery parition.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;After the clone, you’ll have the same partitions, plus some unallocated space at the end of the disk.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I deleted the recovery partition, then expanded the main partition to fill all of the empty space. Windows 10s built-in disk partition tool can’t expand an NTFS partition, which is why I used gparted.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Restart the computer and boot into the restored Windows 10 environment
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You’ll need to change the storage firmware setting back to RAID mode in order to boot into Windows.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some additional commentary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you only have one USB thumb drive, you can move creation of the Ubuntu drive to between steps 6 and 7, reusing the drive you used for the Reflect restore environment. The reason I suggest two is for troubleshooting. If your newly installed drive can’t boot you can boot into Ubuntu to use the web, create new USB drives, examine the partitions, etc. If you only have the one, and your first attempt fails, you’ll have to swap out the drive physically in between attempts, which is a pain.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For my first attempt at doing the clone, I used gparted and dd within Ubuntu to clone the existing partitions to the backup drive, and then to restore them to the new drive. Windows would not boot after doing this. A Windows rescue disk that I had made prior to starting the backup and restore process was unable to repair the boot problem. I also tried with Acronis True Image 2015, which also failed. So I strongly suggest using Reflect, and not something similar. The switch from SATA to NVME seems to confound a lot of the typical methods of clone and restore.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some internet commentary talks about solutions to booting problems involving turning off Secure Boot, and/or enabling legacy mode booting. I didn’t experiment with changing those settings. It’s possible that changing those settings would have fixed my problems using the Windows rescue disk to repair my dd-cloned boot partition. I doubt it though; I didn’t have any problems booting my repair disk, it just wasn’t able to repair my boot partition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Intel recently released the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/solid-state-drives/solid-state-drives-600p-series.html&quot;&gt;600p&lt;/a&gt; line of SSDs. They use the new NVMe interface, and offer an intermediate level of performance between SATA drives and the other NVMe drives on the market (the Samsung 950 Pro, the Toshiba RD400). But whereas the 950 pro will set you back about $315 for a 512 GB model, at the time of writing you can get a 512 GB 600p from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microcenter.com/product/468436/600p_512GB_M2_Internal_SSD&quot;&gt;Microcenter&lt;/a&gt; for only $170, which is quite competitive with SATA 3 drive prices. It seemed like a good deal to me, and induced me to upgrade. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See, for instance reddit posts by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Dell/comments/3zfqmx/samsung_950_pro_speed_on_dell_xps_13_9350/&quot;&gt;/u/kentjapan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Dell/comments/4tyqof/does_the_xps_13_9350_with_128_gb_ssd_support_pcie/&quot;&gt;/u/jerkel&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Dell/comments/4cbsn2/xps_13_9350_nvme_issue_after_bios_update/&quot;&gt;/u/soymilk&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>About the Work Timer</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/08/12/about-the-work-timer/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/08/12/about-the-work-timer</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made the work timer primarily as an exercise to learn some javascript and CSS, but I thought it might be worth describing how I use it, in case anyone stumbles upon it and is curious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often work with a variation of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro Timer&lt;/a&gt; productivity system. For the first 25 minutes after starting work, I keep working regardless of how frustrated I feel. After the first 25 minutes, I take a 5-10 minute break whenever I feel even a little frustrated. It helps me perserve long enough when starting work to get into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)&quot;&gt;flow&lt;/a&gt;, but break often enough that I don’t get excessively fatigued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existing pomodoro timers I found online didn’t work great with my modifications. At the end of a work period they would tend to either alert until the user interacted with the timer, or they would alert and then automatically go into the following break period. Either made it necessary for me to interact with the software at the end of the initial work period, which would sometimes knock me out of flow. So at the end of a work or break period, my timer makes a minimally obtrusive alert, then keeps counting the time. When I’ve decided I want to stop, I can tell the timer I’ve switched to a different period. It also tracks my history, so I can see how much actual working I’m doing every day, essentially gamifying my productivity efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a pure productivity standpoint writing a customized timer would have been a huge loser (given how much time I spent learning javascript and CSS). But it was a great project for learning. And I got a tool I can actually use as a bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hello World!</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/08/11/hello-world/"/>
   <updated>2016-08-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/08/11/hello-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I created this site primarily as a learning exercise. I program a lot, but, unlike a lot of other programmers, what I program typically has nothing whatsoever to do with the world wide web. Or even a corporate intra-web. Given the ubiquity of web apps I thought it might be a good idea to be at least minimally familiar with web programming. Enough that when developers talk about web stuff my blank uncomprehending stare doesn’t make them wonder if I really know how to program at all. Backend web stuff is actually pretty similar to the stuff I do every day, so for me this was mostly about the front-end, client-side web. Since for me learning by doing is the only way to go, I needed to make a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with using Jekyll to generate a static site, since that seemed like the easiest possible way to get a useful site. After realizing just how easy that was, I realized I needed a more substantial project if I actually wanted to learn anything. I’ve been using Pomodoro timers as a productivity tool recently, and decided that writing my own would make a good project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After building the site it seemed silly not to actually publish it, so here it is. I guess I have a blog now. I don’t know that I will end up posting with any regularity, but who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
